Good afternoon.
مساء الخير.
I am not a farmer.
أنا لست مزارعاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm not. I'm a parent, I'm a resident and I'm a teacher.
أنا لست كذلك. أنا أب، أنا مقيم ومعلّم.
And this is my world.
وهذا عالمي.
And along the way I've started noticing --
وخلال الطريق بدأت بالملاحظة --
I'm on my third generation of kids --
أنا في الجيل الثالث من أطفالي --
that they're getting bigger.
بأنهم يصبحون أكبر
They're getting sicker.
وأكثر مرضاً.
In addition to these complexities,
وزيادة على هذه التعقيدات،
I just learned that 70 percent of the kids that I see
تعلّمت أن 70 بالمئة من هؤلاء الأطفال الذين أراهم
who are labeled learning disabled would not have been
والمصنفون بأنهم صعيبو التعلّم لم يكونوا
had they had proper prenatal nutrition.
ليحظوا بالرعاية المناسبة من الوالدين.
The realities of my community are simple. They look like this.
الواقع في مجتمعي بسيط. يبدون مثل هكذا.
Kids should not have to grow up and look at things like this.
الأطفال يجب أن لا يكبروا وينظروا للأشياء بهذا الشكل.
And as jobs continue to leave my community,
وباستمرار ذهاب فرص العمل من مجتمعي،
and energy continues to come in, be exported in,
والطاقة تستمر بالدخول، وتصدر إلى الداخل
it's no wonder that really some people refer to the South Bronx as a desert.
ليس من العجب أن بعض الناس يسمّون جنوب برونكس بالصحراء.
But I'm the oldest sixth grader you'll ever meet,
لكن أنا أكبر طالب في الصف الثالث قد تقابلونه،
so I get up every day with this tremendous amount of enthusiasm
وبالتالي أستيقظ كل يوم بكمية هائلة من الحماس
that I'm hoping to share with you all today.
الذي آمل أن أشاركه معكم اليوم.
And with that note, I come to you with this belief
ومع تلك الملاحظة، آتي لكم بهذا الاعتقاد
that kids should not have to leave their communities
أن الأطفال يجب ألا يغادروا مجتمعاتهم
to live, learn and earn in a better one.
كي يعيشوا، ويتعلّموا ويكسبوا في مجتمع أفضل.
So I'm here to tell you a story about me
لذلك أنا هنا لأخبركم بقصة عني
and this wall that I met outside, which I'm now bringing inside.
وهذا الجدار الذي تعرفت عليه في الخارج، والذي أجلبه الآن للداخل.
And it starts with three people.
وقد بدأ بثلاثة أشخاص.
The crazy teacher -- that's me on the left,
المعلّم المجنون -- هذا أنا على اليسار،
I dress up pretty, thank you, my wife, I love you for getting a good suit --
ألبس بأناقة، شكراً لك، زوجتي، أحبك لجلبك بدلة جيدة --
my passionate borough president
رئيس حيي المتحمس
and a guy named George Irwin from Green Living Technologies
ورجل اسمه جورج اروين من تقنيات الحياة الخضراء
who helped me with my class
الذي ساعدني مع طلاب الصف
and helped me get involved with this patented technology.
وأشركني في هذه التقنية ذات براءة الاختراع.
But it all starts with seeds in classrooms,
لكن كل شيء بدأ بالبذور في الفصول،
in my place, which looks like this.
في مكاني يبدو كهذا.
And I'm here today hoping that my reach will exceed my grasp.
أنا هنا اليوم آملاً أن مد يدي يتعدى قبضتي.
And that's really what this is all about.
وهذا حقيقةً هو كل ما هو عليه.
And it starts with incredible kids like this,
وبدأت مع طلاب رائعين مثل هؤلاء،
who come early and stay late.
يأتون مبكراً ويبقون حتى وقت متأخر.
All of my kids are either IEP or ELL learners,
كل طلاَبي هم إما طلاب برامج التعليم الفردي أو تعليم لغة انجليزية "IEP,ELL"
most come with a lot of handicaps,
معظمهم يأتون بالعديد من المعوقات،
most are homeless and many are in foster care.
معظمهم بلا بيوت وكثير منهم في دور الأيتام.
Almost all of my kids live below poverty.
كل طلابي تقريبا يعيشون تحت الفقر.
But with those seeds, from day one, we are growing in my classroom,
لكن مع هذه البذور، من اليوم الأول، ونحن نزرعها في الفصل،
and this is what it looks like in my classroom.
وهكذا تبدوا في الفصل.
And you see how attentive these kids are to these seeds.
وترون كيف أن هؤلاء الأطفال مهتمون بهذه البذور.
And then you notice that those seeds become farms across the Bronx that look like this.
ثم تلاحظ كيف أن تلك البذور تصبح مزارع في برونكس تبدو هكذا.
But again, I am not a farmer. I'm a teacher.
لكن مرة أخرى، أنا لست مزارعاً، أنا معلّم
And I don't like weeding, and I don't like back-breaking labor.
ولا أحب الحشيش، ولا أحب العمل الشاق الذي يقصم الظهر.
So I wanted to figure out how I could get this kind of success
لذلك فكرت كيف أحول هذا النوع من النجاح
into something small, like this,
إلى شيء صغير، مثل هذا،
and bring it into my classroom so that handicapped kids could do it,
وجلبه إلى صفي بحيث يستطيع المعاقون القيام به،
kids who didn't want to be outside could do it,
أطفال لم يريدوا أن يكونوا بالخارج استطاعوا القيام به،
and everyone could have access.
والجميع يستطيع الوصول.
So I called George Irwin, and what do you know?
لذا اتصلت بجورج ايرون، وخمنوا ماذا؟
He came to my class and we built an indoor edible wall.
جاء إلى صفي وبنينا جدار داخليا قابلا للأكل.
And what we do is we partner it with authentic learning experiences,
وما نفعله هو إشراكه في تجارب علمية موثقة،
private-based learning.
على أساس تعليمي خاص.
And lo and behold, we gave birth to
والمفاجأة أننا أنشأنا
the first edible wall in New York City.
أول جدار داخلي قابل للأكل في مدينة نيويورك.
So if you're hungry, get up and eat.
لذا إذا كنت جائعاً، قم وكل.
You can do it right now. My kids play cow all the time.
بإمكانك فعلها الآن. أطفالي يلعبون دور البقرة طوال الوقت.
Okay? But we were just getting started,
حسناً؟ لكننا للتو بدأنا.
the kids loved the technology,
الأطفال أحبّوا التقنية،
so we called up George and we said, "We gotta learn more!"
لذا اتصلنا بجورج وقلنا،"يجب أن نتعلّم أكثر!"
Now, Mayor Bloomberg, thank you very much, we no longer need work permits,
الآن، شكراً جزيلا عمدة بلومبرج، لم نعد نحتاج رخص عمل،
which comes with slices and bonded contractors -- we're available for you --
التي تأتي مع شرائح من المتعاقدين المضمونين بسندات -- نحن متفرغين لكم --
We decided to go to Boston.
قررنا أن نذهب لبوسطن.
And my kids, from the poorest congressional district in America,
وأطفالي، من أفقر مقاطعة انتخابية في أمريكا،
became the first to install a green wall,
صرنا أول من ركب جدار أخضر،
designed by a computer, with real-live learning tools,
مصمما بالحاسوب، مع أدوات تعلم حيّة،
21 stories up -- if you're going to go visit it,
بطول 21 طابقا -- إذا كنت ستزوره
it's on top of the John Hancock building.
إنه على سطح بناية جون هانكوك.
But closer to home, we started installing these walls in schools
لكن بالقرب من موطننا، بدأنا بتركيب هذه الجدران في المدارس
that look like this with lighting like that,
والتي تبدوا هكذا، مع إضاءة كتلك،
real LED stuff, 21st-century technology.
مع صمام متألق حقيقي، وتقنية القرن21.
And what do you know? We made 21st century money,
وخمنوا ماذا؟ كسبنا نقود القرن ال 21،
and that was groundbreaking. Wow!
وذلك كان فتحا. واو!
This is my harvest, people.
هذا حصادي، ياعالم.
And what do you do with this food? You cook it!
وماذا نفعل بالطعام؟ نطبخه!
And those are my heirloom students making heirloom sauce,
وهؤلاء طلاب الإيرلوم يصنعون صلصة الإيرلوم،
with plastic forks, and we get it into the cafeteria,
مع الشوك البلاستيكية، ونأخذها إلى الكافيتريا،
and we grow stuff and we feed our teachers.
و نزرع الأشياء ونطعم أساتذتنا.
And that is the youngest nationally certified
وتلك أصغر قوة عمل موثقة وطنية
workforce in America with our Bronx Borough President.
في أمريكا مع رئيس حي برونكس.
And what'd we do then? Well, I met nice people like you,
و ماذا نفعل اذا؟ حسنا تعرفت على أشخاص لطيفين مثلكم،
and they invited us to the Hamptons.
ودعونا إلى الـهامبتونز.
So I call this "from South Bronx to Southampton."
لذلك أسمّي هذا " من جنوب برونكس إلى جنوب هامبتون."
And we started putting in roofs that look like this,
وبدأنا نضع الأسقف التي تبدوا هكذا،
and we came in from destitute neighborhoods
وأتينا من أحياء معدمة
to start building landscape like this, wow! People noticed.
لبناء مشاهد مثل هذه، واو! الناس لاحظوا.
And so we got invited back this past summer,
لذا دُعينا في الصيف الماضي،
and we actually moved into the Hamptons,
وانتقلنا حقاً إلى هامبتونز،
payed 3,500 dollars a week for a house, and we learned how to surf.
دفعت لنا 3500 دولار أسبوعيا للمنزل، وتعلمنا ركوب الأمواج.
And when you can do stuff like this --
وعندما تستطيع عمل أشياء كهذه --
These are my kids putting in this technology,
هؤلاء طلابي يثبتون هذه التقنية،
and when you can build a roof that looks like that
وبإمكاننا بناء سقف يبدو هكذا
on a house that looks like that
على منزل يبدو هكذا
with sedum that looks like this,
مع أزهار تبدو هكذا،
this is the new green graffiti.
هذه هي الجداريات الخضراء الجديدة.
So, you may wonder what does a wall like this
لذا قد تتعجبون ماذا يمكن حقاً أن يفعله جدار كهذا
really do for kids, besides changing landscapes and mindsets?
للطلاب، باستثناء تغيير المشاهد الطبيعية والعقليات؟
Okay, I'm going to tell you what it does.
حسناً، سأخبركم ماذا يفعل.
It gets me to meet incredible contractors like this,
مكنني من التعرف على متعاقدين رائعين مثل هؤلاء،
Jim Ellenberger from Ellenberger Services.
جيم إلنبرغر من خدمات إلنبرغر.
And this is where it becomes true triple bottom line.
وهنا حيث أصبح خطا سفلي ثلاثي.
Because Jim realized that these kids, my future farmers,
لأن جيم أدرك أن هؤلاء الطلاب، مزارعيّ المستقبلييّن،
really had the skills he needed to build affordable housing
لديهم المهارات الحقيقية التي يحتاجها لبناء سكن بأسعار معقولة
for New Yorkers, right in their own neighborhood.
لسكان نيويرك، في حيهم الخاص.
And this is what my kids are doing, making living wage.
وهذا مايفعله طلابي، يصنعون لقمة عيشهم.
Now, if you're like me, you live in a building, there are seven guys
الآن، إن كنتم مثلي، تعيشون في بناية، هناك سبعة رجال
out of work looking to manage a million dollars.
خارج العمل يريدون السيطرة على ملايين الدولارات.
I don't have it. But if you need a toilet fixed
لا أملكها. لكن إن احتجت إلى تصليح حمام
or, you know, some shelving, I gotta wait six months
أو كما تعلمون، ترفيف، يجب أن أنتظر ستة أشهر
for an appointment with someone who drives a much nicer car than me.
لأخذ موعد مع شخص يقود سيارة أفضل بكثير مني.
That's the beauty of this economy.
هذا جمال هذا الإقتصاد.
But my kids are now licensed and bonded in trade.
لكن طلابي الآن مرخص لديهم سندات تجارية.
And that's my first student to open up, the first in his family to have a bank account.
وهذا أول طلابي، و أول من فتح حسابا بنكيا في عائلته.
This immigrant student is the first one in his family to use an ATM.
هذا الطالب المهاجر هو الأول في عائلته الذي استخدم الصرافة.
And this is the true triple bottom line,
وهذا هو الخط السفلي الثلاثي الحقيقي،
because we can take neighborhoods that were abandoned and destitute
لأننا نستطيع أن نأخذ أحياء مهجورة و معدمة
and turn them into something like this with interiors like this.
ونحولها لشيء مثل هذا، مظهر داخلي مثل هذا.
Wow! People noticed. And notice they did.
واو! الناس لاحظوا. ولاحظوا.
So CNN called, and we were delighted to have them come to our farmer's market.
لذا اتصلت الـ سي ان ان، وكنا سعيدين بقدومهم إلى متجرنا الزراعي.
And then when Rockefeller Center said, NBC,
ثم حين قال مركز روكفلر، الإن بي سي،
could you put this thing up on the walls? We were delighted.
هل يمكن وضع هذه الأشياء على الجدار؟ كنا سعيدين.
But this, I show you, when kids from the poorest congressional district in America
لكن هذا، أعرضه لكم، عندما كان طلاب أفقر مقاطعة انتخابية أمريكية
can build a 30-foot by 15-foot wall,
يستطيعون بناء جدار بأبعاد 30 قدما و15قدما،
design it, plant it and install it in the heart of New York City,
تصميمه وزرعه وتركيبه في قلب مدينة نيويورك،
that's a true "sí se puede" moment.
هذه لحظة "نعم يمكنك ذلك!" حقيقية.
Really scholastic, if you ask me.
تعليمي حقاً، إن سألتني.
But this is not a Getty image.
لكن هذه ليست صورة من "Getty"
That's a picture I took of my Bronx Borough President,
هذه صورة أخذتها لرئيس حي برونكس،
addressing my kids in his house, not the jailhouse,
يخاطب طلابي في منزله، وليس في السجن.
making them feel a part of it.
يجعلهم يشعرون بأنهم جزء منه.
That's our State Senator Gustavo Rivera and Bob Bieder,
هذا سيناتور الولاية جوستافو ريفيرا و بوب بيدر
coming to my classroom to make my kids feel important.
قدما لصفي لإشعار طلابي بأهميتهم.
And when the Bronx Borough President shows up
وعندما ظهر رئيس حي برونكس
and the State Senator comes to our class,
وسيناتور الولاية يأتي إلى فصلنا،
believe you me, the Bronx can change attitudes now.
صدقوني، يستطيع برونك تغيير المواقف الآن.
We are poised, ready, willing and able
نحن مستعدون وجاهزون وراغبين وقادرون
to export our talent and diversity in ways we've never even imagined.
على تصدير موهبتنا وتنوعنا بطرق لم نحلم بها أبداً.
And when the local senator gets on the scale in public
وعندما اعتلى السيناتور المحلّي الميزان في العلن
and says he's got to lose weight, so do I!
وقال يجب عليه أن يفقد الوزن، وأنا كذلك!
And I tell you what, I'm doing it and so are the kids.
وسأقول لكم ماذا، أنا أعمل على ذلك وكذلك الطلاب.
Okay? And then celebrities started.
حسناً؟ بدأ المشاهير.
Produce Pete can't believe what we grow.
المنتج بيتي لم يصدق ماذا استطعنا أن نزرع.
Lorna Sass came and donated books.
لورينا ساس جاءت وتبرعت بكتب.
Okay? We're feeding seniors.
حسناً؟ ونحن نطعم كبار السن.
And when we realized that we were growing for food justice in the South Bronx,
وعندما أدركنا أننا نزرع لعدالة الطعام في جنوب برونكس،
so did the international community.
وكذلك المجتمع الدولي.
And my kids in the South Bronx were repped in
وطلابي في جنوب برونكس كانوا المتحدثين في
the first international green roof conference.
أول مؤتمر عالمي للأسقف الخضراء.
And that's just great.
وذلك فعلاً رائع.
Except what about locally?
لكن ماذا عن المحلي؟
Well, we met this woman, Avis Richards, with the Ground Up Campaign.
حسناً، تعرفنا على امرأة، أفيس ريتشارد، مع حملة غراوند أب.
Unbelievable! Through her, my kids,
أمر لا يصدق! ومن خلالها، طلابي،
the most disenfranchised and marginalized,
الأكثر حرماناً وتهميشاً،
were able to roll out 100 gardens to New York City public schools.
كانوا قادرين على بسط 100 حديقة مدرسية في مدينة نيويورك.
That's triple bottom line! Okay?
ذلك الخط الثلاثي السفلي! حسنا؟
A year ago today, I was invited to the New York Academy of Medicine.
قبل عام من اليوم، كنت مدعوا إلى أكاديمية نيويورك للطب.
I thought this concept of designing a strong and healthy New York
فكرت في هذا المفهوم لتصميم نيويورك قوية وصحية
made sense, especially when the resources were free.
من المنطقي، خاصة عندما تكون المصادر مجانية.
So thank you all and I love them.
لذا شكراً للجميع و أحبهم.
They introduced me to the New York City Strategic Alliance for Health,
قدموني إلى التحالف الإستراتيجي للصحة في نيويورك
again, free resources, don't waste them.
مرة أخرى، مصادر مجانية، لاتهدرها.
And what do you know? Six months later,
وماذا تعرف؟ بعد ستة أشهر،
my school and my kids were awarded the first ever
مدرستي وطلابي للمرة الأولى على الإطلاق كرّموا
high school award of excellence for creating a healthy school environment.
جائزة المدارس الثانوية للإمتياز لصناعة بيئة صحية مدرسية.
The greenest class in New York City.
الصف الأكثر خضرة في مدينة نيويورك.
But more importantly is my kids learned to get,
لكن الأهم هو أن طلّابي تعلّموا الأخذ
they learned to give.
وتعلّموا العطاء.
And we took the money that we made from our farmer's market,
و أخذنا النقود التي صنعنا من متجرنا الزراعي،
and started buying gifts for the homeless
وبدأنا بشراء هدايا للمتشردين
and for needy around the world.
و للمحتاجين في العالم.
So we started giving back.
وبدأنا بإعادة العطاء.
And that's when I realized that the greening of America
وهذا عندما بدأت بإدراك أن خضرة أمريكا
starts first with the pockets, then with the heart
تبدأ أولاً بالجيوب، ثم بالقلب
and then with the mind.
ثم بالعقل.
So we were onto something, and we're still onto something.
كنا نعمل شيئاً، ولازلنا نعمل.
And thank God Trinity Wall Street noticed,
وحمداً لله أن شارع جدار الثالوث لاحظوا،
because they gave us the birth of Green Bronx Machine.
لأنهم ولّدوا لنا ماكينة برونكس الخضراء.
We're 3,000 strong right now.
نحن أقوى الآن ب 3000 مرة.
And what does it really do?
وما يفعله ذلك حقيقة؟
It teaches kids to re-vision their communities,
يعلّم الطلّاب إعادة النظر في مجتمعاتهم،
so when they grow up in places like this, they can imagine it like this.
حتى عندما يكبرون في أماكن مثل هذه، بإمكانهم تخيلها هكذا.
And my kids, trained and certified --
وطلّابي، مدربون و موثقون--
Ma, you get the tax abatement. Thank you, Mayor Bloomberg --
حسناً، نحصل على تخفيض الضرائب. شكراً لك، عمدة بلومبرج --
can take communities that look like this and convert them into things that look like that,
بالإمكان أخذ مجتمعات تبدو هكذا وتحويلها إلى أشياء تبدو هكذا،
and that to me, people, is another true "sí se puede" moment.
وهذا بالنسبة لي، أيها الناس، هو لحظة "نعم يمكنك ذلك!" أخرى.
Now, how does it start? It starts in schools.
الآن كيف تبدأ؟ تبدأ في المدارس.
No more little Knicks and little Nets.
لا مزيد من المواهب الصغيرة والشبكات الصغيرة.
Group by broccoli, group by your favorite vegetable,
مجموعة القرنبيط، تصنيف حسب الخضار المفضلة،
something you can aspire to.
شيء بالإمكان الطموح له.
Okay? And these are my future farmers of America,
حسناً؟ هؤلاء هم مزارعيّ المستقبلييّن لأمريكا،
growing up in Brook Park on 141st Street,
نزرع في متنزه بروك على شارع 141،
the most migrant community in America.
التجمع الأكبر للمهاجرين في أمريكا.
When tenacious little ones learn how to garden like this,
عندما يتعلم الصغار المعاندون كيف يزرعون هكذا،
it's no wonder we get fruit like that.
لاعجب أن نحصل على فاكهة مثل هذه.
And I love it! And so do they.
و أحبها! وكذلك هم.
And we're building teepees in neighborhoods that were burning down.
نحن نبني خيام التيبي في الأحياء التي كانت تحترق.
And that's a true "sí se puede" moment.
وهذه لحظة "نعم يمكنك ذلك!" حقيقة.
And again, Brook Park feeds hundreds of people
ومرة أخرى، متنزه بروك يطعم المئات من الناس
without a food stamp or a fingerprint.
بدون طبعة طعام أو بصمة اصبع.
The poorest congressional district in America,
المنطقة الأشد فقراً في أمريكا،
the most migratory community in America, we can do this.
المجتمع الأكثر في عدد المهاجرين في أمريكا، بإمكاننا فعل هذا.
Bissel Gardens is cranking out food in epic proportions,
مزارع بازلاء تضخ الطعام بكميات هائلة،
moving kids into an economy they never imagined.
تحرك الأطفال إلى اقتصاد لم يكونوا يحلمون به.
Now, somewhere over the rainbow, my friends,
الآن، في مكان ما فوق قوس قزح، أصدقائي،
is the South Bronx of America. And we're doing it.
إنه جنوب برونكس الأمريكية. ونحن نفعلها.
How does it start? Well, look at Jose's attention to detail.
كيف بدأت؟ حسناً انظروا إلى انتباه خوسيه للتفاصيل.
Thank God Omar knows that carrots come from the ground,
الحمد لله أن عمر يعرف أن الجزر يأتي من الأرض،
and not aisle 9 at the supermarket
وليس من الجناح 9 في السوبرماركت
or through a bullet-proof window or through a piece of styrofoam.
وليس من خلال زجاج مضاد للرصاص أو خلال قطعة من الستايروفوم.
And when Henry knows that green is good, so do I.
وعندما عرف هنري أن الأخضر جيد، وكذلك أنا.
And when you expand their palates, you expand their vocabulary.
وعندما توسع أذواقهم، توسع مفرداتهم.
And most importantly, when you put big kids together with little kids,
و الأهم، عندما تضع الأطفال الكبار والصغار معاً،
you get the big fat white guy out of the middle, which is cool,
تحصل على رجل كبير وسمين في المنتصف، وهو رائع،
and you create this kind of accountability amongst peers, which is incredible.
وتصنع ذلك النوع من الإعتمادية بين الأقران، وهو شيء رائع.
God, I'm going to run out of time, so I've gotta keep it moving.
رباه، سينتهي الوقت مني، لذا يجب أن أبقيها متحركة.
But this is my weekly paycheck for kids; that's our green graffiti.
وهذا الراتب الأسبوعي لطلابي، وهذه الجداريات الخضراء.
This is what we're doing.
هذا ما نفعله.
And behold the glory and bounty that is Bronx County.
شاهدوا المجد والسخاء والهبة التي هي عليها مقاطعة برونكس.
Nothing thrills me more than to see kids pollinating plants instead of each other.
لاشيء يذهلني أكثر من مشاهدة الأطفال يلقحون الأزهار بدلا من بعضهم البعض.
I gotta tell you, I'm a protective parent.
يجب أن أقول لكم، أنا أب أحب الحماية.
But those kids are the kids who are now putting
لكن أولئك الأطفال هم أطفال يضعون
pumpkin patches on top of trains.
بقع اليقطين على القطارات.
We're also designing coin ponds for the rich and affluent.
ونحن أيضاً نصمم برك نقدية للأغنياء والميسورين.
We're also becoming children of the corn,
وأصبحنا أيضاً أطفال الذرة،
creating farms in the middle of Fordham Road for awareness
نصنع مزارع في وسط طريق فوردهام للتوعية.
and window bottles out of garbage.
وعلب نوافذ من القمامة.
Now I don't expect every kid to be a farmer,
الآن لا أتوقع من كل طفل أن يكون مزارعاً،
but I expect you to read about it, write about it, blog about it, offer outstanding customer service.
لكن أتوقع منكم أن تقرؤا عنها، تكتبوا عنها، تدونوها، توفروا خدمة زبائن بارزة.
I expect them to be engaged, and man, are they!
أتوقع منهم أن يكونوا مرتبطين، ويارجل، إنهم كذلك!
So that's my incredible classroom, that's the food.
وهذا فصل رائع، هذا الطعام.
Where does it go? Zero miles to plate, right down into the cafeteria.
أين يذهب؟ صفر من الأميال للصحن، وصولا للكافيتريا.
Or more importantly, to local shelters,
أو للأهم، للملاجئ المحلية،
where most of our kids are getting one to two meals a day.
حيث يأكل معظم طلابنا وجبة أو اثنتين كل يوم.
And we're stepping it up.
ونحن نقوم بترقيته.
No Air Jordans were ever ruined on my farm.
لم تخرب أي أحدذية إير جوردان في مزرعتي مطلقاً.
And in his day, a million dollar gardens and incredible installations.
وفي يومه، تركيب حدائق رائعة بقيمة مليون دولار.
Let me tell you something, people.
دعوني أخبركم شيئاً، أيها الناس.
This is a beautiful moment.
هذه لحظة جميلة.
Black field, brown field, toxic waste field, battlefield --
حقل أسود، حقل بني، حقل فضلات سمية، حقل الحرب --
we're proving in the Bronx that you can grow anywhere, on cement.
أثبتنا أنك تستطيع أن تزرع في أي مكان في برونكس، على الإسمنت.
And we take orders for flowers. I'm putting the bake sale to shame.
ونستلم طلبات ورد. أنا أجعل بيع الخبز عارا.
We take orders now. I'm booking for the spring.
نحن نأخذ الطلبات الآن. وسأحجز للربيع.
And these were all grown from seeds. We're learning everything.
وهذه كلها زرعت من البذور. نحن نتعلم كل شيء.
And again, when you can take kids from backgrounds as diverse
ومرة أخرى, عندما تستطيع أخذ طلاب من كل نوع
as this to do something as special as this,
لعمل شيء مميز كهذا،
we're really creating a moment.
نحن فعلا نصنع لحظة.
Now, you may ask about these kids.
الآن، قد تسألون عن هؤلاء الطلاب.
Forty percent attendance to 93 percent attendance.
نسبة حضور ما بين 40 و93 في المئة.
All start overage and under-credit.
كلهم بدأوا بسن كبير ورصيد قليل.
They are now, my first cohort is all in college, earning a living wage.
هم الآن، أول مجموعة في الجامعة، يكسبون معاشهم.
The rest are scheduled to graduate this June.
والباقين مجدولين للتخرج في يونيو القادم.
Happy kids, happy families, happy colleagues.
أطفال سعداء، عوائل سعيدة، زملاء سعداء.
Amazed people. The glory and bounty that is Bronx County.
أشخاص مدهشون. المجد والسخاء التي هي عليه مقاطعة برونكس.
Let's talk about mint. Where is my mint?
لنتكلّم عن النعناع. أين نعناعي؟
I grow seven kinds of mint in my class.
أزرع سبعة أنواع من النعناع في فصلي.
Mojitos, anybody? I'll be at Telepan later.
موجيتوس، أي شخص؟ سأكون على التليبان فيما بعد.
But, understand this is my intellectual Viagra.
لكن، هذه بالنسبة لي فياغرا فكرية.
Ladies and gentlemen, I gotta move quick, but understand this:
سيداتي وسادتي، يجب أن أتحرك بسرعة، لكن أرجو أن تفهموا مايلي:
The borough that gave us baggy pants and funky fresh beats
الإدارة التي أعطتنا السراويل الكيسية، واللحن الطازج الغريب
is becoming home to the organic ones.
أصبحت منزلاً للعضوية.
My green [unclear] 25,000 pounds of vegetables,
خضرواتي الخضراء التي تزن 25،000 باوند،
I'm growing organic citizens, engaged kids.
أنا أنمي مواطنين عضويين، وطلاب مرتبطين.
So help us go from this to this.
لذا ساعدونا لنتحول من هذا لذاك.
Self-sustaining entities, 18 months return on investment,
المكونات ذاتية التحمل، مدة إستعادة الاستثمار هي 18 شهرا،
plus we're paying people living wage and health benefits,
وكذلك ندفع للناس أجرة و فوائد صحية،
while feeding people for pennies on the dollar.
بينما إطعام الناس بالقروش فضلاً على الدولارات.
Martin Luther King said that people need to be uplifted with dignity.
قال مالكوم لوثر كينغ أن الناس بحاجة أن يرتقوا بكرامة.
So here in New York, I urge you, my fellow Americans,
لذا هنا في نيويرك، أنا أحثكم، رفاقي الأمريكيين،
to help us make America great again.
على مساعدتنا لجعل أمريكا عظيمة مرة أخرى.
It's simple. Share your passion.
إنه بسيطة. شارك عواطفك.
It's real easy. Go see these two videos, please.
بسيطة جداً. إذهبوا لرؤية الفيديو، رجاءً.
One got us invited to the White House, one's a recent incarnation.
شخص ما أدى إلى دعوتنا إلى البيت الأبيض، تجسيد حديث لشخص ما.
And most importantly, get the biggest bully out of schools.
والأهم، إخراج أكبر متنمر من المدارس.
This has got to go tomorrow.
هذا يجب أن يذهب غداً.
People, you can all do that.
أيها الناس، يمكنكم جميعاً فعل ذلك.
Keep kids out of stores that look like this.
أبقوا الطلاب خارج متاجر تبدو كهذه.
Make them a healthy plate,
اصنعوا لهم طبق صحي،
especially if you can pick it off the wall in your own classroom -- delicioso!
خاصة إذا كنتم تستطيعون التقاطه من الجدار الخاص بصفكم -- لذيذ!
Model good behavior. Get them to a green cart.
اصنع القدوة في السلوك الجيد. اذهب بهم للسلال الخضراء.
Big kids love strawberries and bananas.
الطلاب الكبار يحبون الفراولة والموز.
Teach them entrepreneurship. Thank God for GrowNYC.
علّمهم ريادة الأعمال. حمدا لله على GrowNYC..
Let them cook. Great lunch today, let them do culinary things.
دعهم يطبخون. غداء عظيم اليوم، دعهم يؤدون مهام مطبخية.
But most importantly, just love them.
لكن الأهم، فقط أحبهم.
Nothing works like unconditional love.
لاشيء يعمل مثل حب لا مشروط.
So, my good friend Kermit said it's not easy being green.
لذا، صديقي كرميت يقول إنه ليس بالسهل أن تكون أخضر.
It's not. I come from a place where kids can buy
إنه ليس كذلك. آتي من مكان حيث الأطفال يستطيعون شراء
35 flavors of blunt wrap at any day of the moment,
35 نكهة من لفائف السيجار في أي لحظة من اليوم،
where ice cream freezers are filled with slushy malt liquor.
حيث تمتلئ ثلاجات الآيسكريم بخمور شعير ذائبة.
Okay? My dear friend Majora Carter once told me,
حسناً؟ صديقي العزيز ماجورا كارتر مرة قال لي،
we have everything to gain and nothing to lose.
لدينا كل شيء لنكسب، و لاشيء لنخسره.
So here, and at a time when we've gone from
لذا ها نحن هنا، وفي أوقات انتقلنا فيها من
the audacity to hope to hope for some audacity,
الجرأة على الأمل إلى الأمل بجرأة،
I urge you to do something.
أحثكم لتفعلوا شيئاً.
Right now, we're all tadpoles,
الآن، نحن كلنا شراغيف.
but I urge you to become a big frog and take that big, green leap.
لكني أحثكم أن تكونوا ضفادع أكبر وتأخذوا تلك القفزة الكبيرة الخضراء.
I don't care if you're on the left, on the right, up the middle, wherever.
لا يهمني إن كنت على اليسار، على اليمين، في الأعلى في المنتصف، أيّاً كان.
Join me. Use -- I've got a lot of energy. Help me use it.
انضموا إلي. استخدموا -- لدي الكثير من الطاقة. ساعدوني باستخدامها.
We can do something here.
بإمكاننا صنع شيء هنا.
And along the way, please take time to smell the flowers,
وخلال الطريق، أرجوكم خذوا الوقت لشم الورد،
especially if you and your students grew them.
خاصة إذا كنتم أنتم وطلابكم من زرعها.
I'm Steve Ritz, this is Green Bronx Machine.
أنا ستيف ريتز، وهذه غرين برونكس ماشين.
I've got to say thank you to my wife and family, for my kids,
يجب أن أقول شكراً لك زوجتي ولعائلتي، ولطلابي،
thank you for coming every day, and for my colleagues,
شكراً بقدومكم كل يوم، ولزملائي،
believing and supporting me.
الذين آمنوا بي ودعموني.
We are growing our way into a new economy.
نحن نبني طريقنا إلى الإقتصاد الجديد.
Thank you, God bless you and enjoy the day. I'm Steve Ritz.
شكراً لكم، بارك الله فيكم استمتعوا بيومكم. أنا ستيف ريتز.
Sí se puede!
"نعم يمكنك ذلك!"
(Applause)
(تصفيق)